A Guide to the Frederic G. Melcher-Robert Frost Collection,
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series V: Correspondence of Frederic G. Melcher with Various Authors and Publishers
  - Harriet Monroe regrets that she is unable to attend the Robert Frost birthday dinner, 1925 Mar 16 (Box-folder 5:85)
    Harriet Monroe regrets that she is unable to attend the Robert Frost birthday dinner but she wishes to be counted as present in spirit. She sends her greetings to Frost, "May he live long and prosper- and keep on good terms with his muse!"
  - Helen M. Moody, a former pupil of Robert Frost's at Pinkerton Academy, to Mr. Thompson, 1940 Mar 8 (Box-folder 5:86)
    Helen M. Moody, a former pupil of Robert Frost's at Pinkerton Academy, to Mr. Thompson, writes that she is willing to be interviewed about Frost and also suggests that he talk to Miss Sylvia Clark, who was also a teacher at the Academy. See also her note about Frost in Box 3.
  - Anne Carroll Moore thanks Melcher for his participation in her silver anniversary at [the New York Public Library?] (1931); and refers to his beautiful tribute at the Newbery-Caldecott dinner (1948). 1931-1948 (Box-folder 5:87)
  - Marianne Moore appreciates the print of Melcher and herself provided by McDowell and Obolensky. 1958 May 4 (Box-folder 5:88)
  - Stanley Morison, Sheed and Ward Publishers, provides letter of introduction for Thomas F. Burns. 1933 Jan 27 (Box-folder 5:89)
  - Christopher Morley sends a copy of a speech (not present) he has written for "Roger Mifflin", 1919-1943, n.d. (Box-folder 5:90)
    Christopher Morley sends a copy of a speech (not present) he has written for "Roger Mifflin" at the convention to be delivered by Cedric Crowell impersonating Mifflin (1920); returns a completed questionnaire, "Who's Who Among Living American Authors?" to Publishers Weekly (July 5, 1921); book sales concerning The Haunted Bookshop (August 5 & 8, 1921); Melcher discusses the drawbacks of a bibliography, "Booksellers' Reference Library" and mentions he is to be the director of the bookselling course at Columbia University next summer (November 27, 1926); requests Melcher to join as a member and investor in The Foundry on River Street Hoboken, hoping to create a "permanent Cheshire Cheese sort of place," with a printed prospectus (April 15 & 19, 1930); to Ted McCawley, discusses and supplies a list of additional suggestions for the White House Collection (July 12, 1934); mention of the success of Kitty Foyle and the news that Frank Henry is resigning from Lippincotts at the end of the year (December 7 & 11, 1939); congratulates Melcher on the appearance of the new Publishers' Weekly (August 14, 1942); and discusses at length his opposition to the autographing of books by the author, especially in war-time due to the cost and trouble to the author mailing the books back to the purchaser (January 7, 1943).
  - Kathleen Morrison and Theodore Morrison mention an article about Robert Frost in the Scholastic Magazine, 1940-1952 (Box-folder 5:91)
    Kathleen Morrison and Theodore Morrison mention an article about Robert Frost in the Scholastic Magazine which may have a new photograph of Frost and that Frost has just left on a trip to Iowa and Utah (April 3 & 8, 1940); Melcher agrees to speak at the Breadloaf Conference and discusses the relationship of Robert Frost and his publishers (August 14 & 23, 1948); they mention that Robert Frost is concerned about the sale of one of his books with his poem, "Closed for Good" written out, presumably by a friend, as he has learned his lesson about writing out long poems for strangers (November 7, 1949); and Melcher mentions his investigation of Mr. Kauti and his background on Frost's behalf (October 1, 1952).
  - Honore W. Morrow thanks Melcher for his expression of sympathy. 1931 Dec 9 (Box-folder 5:92)
  - Senator Wayne Morse, Oregon, sends a form letter thanking his supporters. 1952 Dec 3 (Box-folder 5:93)
  - Louise Chandler Moulton to Mr. Lauriat, thanks him for his efforts which secured her book earlier than expected. n.y. Jun 12 (Box-folder 5:94)
  - Lewis Mumford agrees to serve as a judge on the Fifty Books Committee (November 9 & 21, 1935); and ultimately agrees to speak for Melcher (December 22, 1935; January 7 & 11, 1936). 1935-1936 (Box-folder 5:95)
  - Ray Nash, Dartmouth College, Department of Art and Archaeology, Hanover, New Hampshire, 1950-1957 (Box-folder 6:1)
    Discusses the upcoming auction of Twilight by Robert Frost and his hopes that Dartmouth can secure the book (December 4, 1950); asks Melcher if he hasn't got some article or note on some aspect of printing or the book trade, suitable for Printing and Graphic Arts (1957).
  - Robert Nathan warns that someone is impersonating him in Chicago (May [16],1933); and refers to the sales of his book, The Road of Ages, as reported in the English Publishers' Circular May 10, 1935). 1933, 1935 (Box-folder 6:2)
  - Scott Nearing responds to a form letter from Melcher, [1934 Dec 28] (Box-folder 6:3)
    Scott Nearing responds to a form letter from Melcher posing the question, "What would be your one-book prescription for country-wide 'required' reading for this coming year?" with Rajani Palme Dutt's book, Fascism and Social Revolution.
  - W.A. Neilson responds to a form letter from Melcher, 1935, 1940 (Box-folder 6:4)
    W.A. Neilson responds to a form letter from Melcher posing the question, "What would be your one-book prescription for country-wide 'required' reading for this coming year?" with A Primer for Tomorrow by Dean Christian Gauss.
  - Robert S. Newdick, professor at Ohio State University, reports on his wonderful four-day visit with Robert Frost and his wife, 1935-1938 (Box-folder 6:5)
    obert S. Newdick, professor at Ohio State University, reports on his wonderful four-day visit with Robert Frost and his wife, both of whom promised assistance with his full-length biography. For his bibliography of Frost, he has joined forces with Mr. Green and Mr. Clymer (September 30, 1935). Melcher helps with questions about one of Frost's poems about shoes, one smelling of Atlantic salt and the other Pacific salt and an anecdote concerning the same poem and T.S. Eliot (December 12 & 16, 1935); Melcher warns Newdick to proceed slowly because both Frosts "have a way of backing away from the responsibility of digging up material from the past" (December 26, 1935; January 3 & 9, 1936); complaints about the style, quantity, and accuracy of Clymer and Green's contributions to the Frost bibliography about which Melcher agrees that Newdick should proceed on his own (January 27, 1936; February 3 & 25, 1936; March 4, 1936); reports on Frost's appearance and reception at Ohio State University and his invitation for Newdick to visit him during the summer (May 25, 1936); Melcher asks for copies of all Newdick's articles about Frost (July 7, 1936); describes his work on articles about Frost, including one on exhibitions and bibliographies of the work of Robert Frost, mentioning Melcher's own checklist in Publishers' Weekly and the fuller descriptions in The Colophon (July 29, 1936); discusses the idea of publishing the prose work of Robert Frost (July 29, August 3 & 5, 1936); questions about whether he should do a biography of Frost for Oxford University Press (November 23, 30, 1937; March 4, 7, 9, 10, 1938); and asks for help on a possible paper about the various types of Frost inscriptions in books (September 15, 19, October 2, 21).
  - A. Edward Newton discusses one second-hand bookstore owner in Indianapolis, 1922-1932 (Box-folder 6:6)
    A. Edward Newton discusses one second-hand bookstore owner in Indianapolis who does not allow anyone to browse in his store, but asks if you need a particular book which he then retrieves for the customer (Apr 20-21, 1922); and sends an advertisement request to Publishers' Weekly for a book, Thomas Hardy- Novelist or Poet? The proceeds from the sale of the book are forwarded to a committee in England in charge of erecting a monument to Thomas Hardy (August 15, 24, 1929).
  - Earle W. Newton answers Melcher's questions about the publication information for The Gold Hesperidee A New Poem by Robert Frost published by The Bibliophile Press, Cortland, New York. 1935 Jul-Aug (Box-folder 6:7)
  - Meredith Nicholson asks Melcher to send Mr. Jackson copies of some of his works (May 18, 1916), 1916-1929, n.d. (Box-folder 6:8)
    Meredith Nicholson asks Melcher to send Mr. Jackson copies of some of his works (May 18, 1916); misses Melcher since he left Indianapolis; saw Stewart, of the W.K. Stewart Company, who did not appear bitter about Melcher leaving Indianapolis; and mentions his book The Valley of Democracy and his work for Scribners (August 21, 1918); discusses his war work and Matthew's review in the newspaper about his writing (September 16, 1918); mention of his work on Indiana, his book And They Lived Happily Ever After and a prospective book on Andrew Jackson (1925 November 12, 16, 23, 27).
  - Blair Niles thanks Melcher for his efforts in awarding her the Constance Lindsay Skinner medal. 1941 March 15 (Box-folder 6:9)
  - Edward J. O'Brien asks Melcher's opinion about his transcript short story selection this year, 1918 Feb 12 (Box-folder 6:10)
    Edward J. O'Brien asks Melcher's opinion about his transcript short story selection this year, because he wants to "make the American public sufficiently self conscious, so that those whose stories have qualities of straightforwardness and direct plot might be encouraged to stop writing down rather than up to the level."
  - Frederick O'Brien discusses the results of the recent vote at the Travel Show concerning travel books. 1922 May 3, 13 (Box-folder 6:11)
  - Walter Pach recommends for reading Les maãitres d'autrefois. Belgique-Hollande by Eugene Fromentin. In English, he believes the title would be something like Old Masters of Belgium and Holland. 1935 Jan 4 (Box-folder 6:12)
  - Edmund Pearson declines to speak at the library meeting at Lake Placid. 1934 May 22 (Box-folder 6:13)
  - Joseph Pennell proposes "The Wonder of Work in War Time" as the subject of his talk (November 2, 1917);, 1917, 1922 (Box-folder 6:14)
    Joseph Pennell proposes "The Wonder of Work in War Time" as the subject of his talk (November 2, 1917); and in most of his correspondence, discusses the Kelmscott Chaucer and the comments of Mr. Hopkins, a New York bookseller, about it (October 6, 7, 16, 18, 20, 29; November 1, 5, 1922)
  - Bliss Perry is unable to give a talk (April 25, 1924), 1924, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 6:15)
    Comments on the White House library book list and makes his own recommendations (1934 July 6; January 10, 1935).
  - William Lyon Phelps cannot accept his invitation for that day (January 3, 1921), 1921, 1934 (Box-folder 6:16)
    William Lyon Phelps cannot accept his invitation for that day (January 3, 1921); and sends his eliminations and additions to the White House library book list (July 2, 1934).
  - Ezra Pound refers to an article in the Publishers' Weekly on censorship, 1927 (Box-folder 6:17)
    Ezra Pound refers to an article in the Publishers' Weekly on censorship and gives his own views on the subject and characterizes the current copyright law as dishonest (May 11, September 6, 1927); responds to a printed note claiming that he acted as an agent for James Joyce with Samuel Roth and his magazine The Two Worlds Monthly (August 6, September 26, 1927); and contributes a paragraph to be published in the Publishers' Weekly protesting the support of magazine publishers for the current copyright law as opposed to the new one proposed by Mr. Vestal, which he feels would be fairer to authors (October 12, 1927).
  - John Barnes Pratt thanks Melcher for his review of A.S. Barnes and Company on its 100th Anniversary, 1938 Mar 15 (Box-folder 6:18)
    ohn Barnes Pratt thanks Melcher for his review of A.S. Barnes and Company on its 100th Anniversary, his friendship, and his efforts on building up the Publishers' Weekly to a "wonderful journal of publishing."
  - Keith Preston promises to write something for the Publishers' Weekly as soon as he can. n.d. (Box-folder 6:19)
  - Herbert Putnam, Library of Congress, appreciates Melcher's note in the Publishers' Weekly, [1939], 1949 (Box-folder 6:20)
    Herbert Putnam, Library of Congress, appreciates Melcher's note in the Publishers' Weekly concerning himself and the need for professional standards in library work (December 3, [1939]) and his presence and remarks at the luncheon (April 12, 1949).
  - William C. Redfield, Secretary of Commerce, to Congressman D.J. O'Connell, cannot accept his invitation due to the press of work. 1919 Apr 21 (Box-folder 6:21)
  - William Marion Reedy tells Melcher he will publish his article on the subject of Publishers and Profiteers in answer to A Book Buyer in his magazine Reedy's Mirror (May 14, 1919) and apologizes for not being able to meet him while he was in St. Louis (March 10, 1920). 1919-1920 (Box-folder 6:22)
  - Aurelia Henry Reinhardt recommends for reading Russia's Iron Age by William Henry Chamberlain. 1935 Jan 15 (Box-folder 6:23)
  - Mary Roberts Rinehart discusses her boys' prospects and her appreciation for his letter and for the way that he ran her little article. n.d. (Box-folder 6:24)
  - Jessie B. Rittenhouse regrets that they will not be able to attend Robert Frost's birthday dinner. [1925] Mar 1 (Box-folder 6:25)
  - Corinne Roosevelt Robinson encloses her review of Roman Bartholomew by Edwin Arlington Robinson. [1923?] Apr 4 (Box-folder 6:26)
  - Edwin Arlington Robinson regrets that he is unable to attend Robert Frost's birthday dinner. 1925 Mar 5 (Box-folder 6:27)
  - Bruce Rogers discusses inaccuracies in The Bookman's Glossary (May 7, 8, 1925), 1920-1957 (Box-folder 6:28)
    Bruce Rogers discusses inaccuracies in The Bookman's Glossary (May 7, 8, 1925); the use of Mrs. Florence Wyman Ivins' portrait of him for an article by Carl Rollins (October 19, November 9, 11, December 2, 1925); questions about subscriptions to the Publishers' Weekly and The Bookman's Journal (December 2, 1925); his opinion of Thomas James Cobden-Sanderson, which aside from the craftsmanship of his bindings, was not a high one, especially concerning his destruction of Sir Emery Walker's property in the Doves Press types; his preference for Jessie Willcox Smith to Arthur Rackham as a children's illustrator, "Rackham is too sentimental and is really for grown-ups- the child wants something simpler... J.W.S. supplies this (however badly, at times) while Rackham furnishes the poetry, all ready-made- he's good at that, of course, but best in his simple head- & tail-pieces- too much 'art' in the others- for children" (October 20, 1926). Bruce Rogers also asks Melcher not to discuss his proposed Prayer Book in Publishers' Weekly at this time (May 20, 1927); encloses [Will] Ransom's article on himself and expresses his appreciation of the entire series of articles done by him (May 3, 1928); mentions Carl Rollins review of The Book of Psalms and a check-list by Alice Lerch (June 18, 20, 1928); thanks Melcher for his subscription to The Odyssey, a new translation by T.E. Lawrence, published by Sir Emery Walker, Wilfred Merton, and Bruce Rogers from Monotype Centaur Type, and asks that an advertisement for the book be placed in Publishers' Weekly (October 8, November 22, 1932); encloses an interview by Bruce Rogers about his work on exhibit at the New York Public Library ([January?] 2, 1954; May 19, 1955); discusses his plans for the October House Classics, with an advance notice and description of the first book, Life of Saint George (March 27, 30, May 26, June 8, 1956); mails a notice that his grand-daughter will begin to sell books of his making (December 31, 1956; January 21, 24, 1957); and includes a brochure, A Remembrance of Bruce Rogers A Gentle Man From Indiana, prepared for friends of Philip and Fanny Duschnes (December 1957).
  - Carl P. Rollins, Yale University Press, recipient of a letter from Melcher in which he asks that a further paragraph about Frost's studies at Harvard be inserted in his article about Robert Frost before its publication. 1930 Mar 4 (Box-folder 6:29)
  - Eleanor Roosevelt invites Melcher to lunch to discuss the White House Library (January 6, 1941) and asks for Melcher's help in securing some books in English for Inamullah Khan, President of the All Pakistan Youth Movement (October 19, 24, 1955). 1941, 1955 (Box-folder 6:30)
  - Leverett Saltonstall, Governor of Massachusetts, thanks Melcher for documents sent to his office. 1943 Nov 10 (Box-folder 6:31)
  - Kate Sanborn to Mr. Lauriat, orders a set of Robert Louis Stevenson's books be sent to her brother for his birthday. [1902] Jul 23 (Box-folder 6:32)
  - Carl Sandburg, Chicago Daily News stationery, sends a letter of introduction for Martha Cochran of New Rochelle (September 7, 1926) 1918-1929, n.d. (Box-folder 6:33)
    Carl Sandburg, Chicago Daily News stationery, sends a letter of introduction for Martha Cochran of New Rochelle (September 7, 1926); and thanks for the volume of Edward Channing's History of the United States with a request for his copy of The Confusion of Tongues (May 11, 17, 1929). Also present is a lengthy typescript review about Carl Sandburg and his work by Clement K. Shorter which appeared in The Sphere, London (July 29, 1918).
  - Frances Clarke Sayers discusses in detail the luncheon given to honor Melcher which was attended by his son, Daniel Melcher, in his stead and the gifts presented to Melcher in honor of his 50th Anniversary. 1945 Jun 15 (Box-folder 6:34)
  - Evelyn Scott thanks Melcher for the invitation to the literary dinner of the New York Library Association at Lake Mohonk on September 28, 1934 (Box-folder 6:35)
    She would love to attend the dinner, but cannot due to the fact that her husband is now in the hospital in England and she must leave earlier than planned.
  - Charles Scribner appreciates very much Melcher's kind words about him after fifty years in the business in the last issue of the Publishers' Weekly. 1925 Jan 27
  - Ellery Sedgwick, The Atlantic Monthly, asks if he knows any librarians or book critics, 1919, 1920 (Box-folder 6:37)
    Ellery Sedgwick, The Atlantic Monthly, asks if he knows any librarians or book critics, further west than Cleveland, to use as a consultant occasionally and mentions Parker material that they hope to publish (March 12, 1919) and discusses their plans for a new bookroom to retail their own publications (September 3, 1920).
  - Elizabeth Shepley Sergeant informs Melcher that she is writing a biography about Robert Frost, 1956-1961 (Box-folder 6:38)
    Elizabeth Shepley Sergeant informs Melcher that she is writing a biography about Robert Frost, focusing on the poetry itself, for Henry Holt and Company. She notes that her friendship with the Frosts dates to 1924 when she first wrote about him in The New Republic and asks Melcher if she could talk with him about Robert Frost at his convenience (February 14, 15, 1956); sends a detailed list of Robert Frost material left with Sergeant by Frederic Melcher on March 10, 1956 (March 21, 1956); asks about the possible location of various files concerning Frost that were removed from the Holt records by various editors or managers before they came to the Princeton Library and the biographical material assembled by Robert S. Newdick (May 27, 31, 1956); writes about the completion and upcoming publication of Robert Frost: The Trial by Existence (September 11, 15, 1959; February 25, March 4, 8, 1960); apologizes that she has mislaid The Mountaineer, January 13, 1928, which she hopes to find (April 29, May 3, 9, 13, 1960; January 3, 6, 1961); and asks permission to send copies of Melcher's letters and Frost material with her files to the University of Virginia Barrett Library which Melcher declines (February 20, 23, 1961).
  - Stuart Sherman writes that he cannot come and speak at Montclair at the present time but might be able to come next winter (May 12, September 26, 1924; February 18, 1925). 1924-1926 (Box-folder 6:39)
  - Upton Sinclair informs Melcher of his compilation of a bibliography of foreign editions and translations of his books (August 26, 1930); and recommends for reading his book, I, Candidate for Governor: and How I Got Licked (January 11, 1935). 1930, 1935 (Box-folder 6:40)
  - Jessie Willcox Smith appreciates Melcher's letter and the check for the poster she made for Children's Book Week. 1919 Nov 22 (Box-folder 6:41)
  - Samuel Francis Smith, autograph copy of verse from America with signature of Smith, 1894 Sep 29 (Box-folder 6:42)
  - Wilbert Snow responds that he will attend the Robert Frost birthday dinner which he later says went really well and asks for the full name of an author that he had reviewed. 1925 Mar 3, Apr 3 (Box-folder 6:43)
  - Paul Standard thanks Melcher for the B.R. Selborne that he secured for him, mentions an anecdote about an autographed book of birthday greetings for W.A. Dwiggins that arrived 78 days early, and refers to his Book Clinic article for Publishers' Weekly. 1937 Jun 12 (Box-folder 6:44)
  - Vilhjalmur Stefansson includes carbons of letters to publishers with his letter to Melcher, 1939 Apr 22 (Box-folder 6:45)
    All about possible books pertaining to Icelandic mythology, discovery and exploration, biographies, biology or botany, etc. that they could sell at a bookstall in the Iceland building at the World's Fair in New York.
  - Lincoln Steffens recommends for common reading, Fascism and Social Revolution by R. Palme-Dutt and as a second choice, John Strachey's Coming Struggle for Power. 1935 Jan 3 (Box-folder 6:46)
  - Adali E. Stevenson thanks the Melchers for their understanding message and support of a dinner at the Waldorf Astoria. 1952, 1956 (Box-folder 6:47)
  - Frederick A. Stokes asks Melcher to be a member of the Frances Hodgson Burnett Memorial Committee to create a "Secret Garden" in Central Park set apart for children "as a nature-study, story-telling centre for children." 1925 Aug 1 (Box-folder 6:48)
  - Philip Duffield Stong agrees to speak before the stout-hearted librarians at Lake Mohonk on the 24th, 1936 Sep 12 (Box-folder 6:49)
    "As to length I venture to suggest that my ignorance will seem just as appalling in fifteen minutes as it will in an hour." He also thanks him for his kind words about Honk the Moose.
  - Mark Sullivan recommends for reading Far Away and Long Ago by W.H. Hudson. 1935 Jan 14 (Box-folder 6:50)
  - Frank Swinnerton thanks Melcher for his kindness during his Montclair engagement (January 7, [1924]), [1924?]-1931 (Box-folder 6:51)
    Sends his third Word from London article to the Publishers' Weekly; tells an anecdote about Edgar Wallace and mentions his book, The Calendar about horse-racing (October 3, November 19, 1929); and hopes to meet him while Melcher is on his trip to England (May 7, 1931).
  - Ida M. Tarbell thanks him for his suggestion about her article on the service that the library can perform for men and women at work "at the machine." 1920 Jan 21 (Box-folder 6:52)
  - Sara Teasdale and her husband happily accept the invitation to the birthday dinner for Robert Frost. 1925 Mar 20 (Box-folder 6:53)
  - Lawrance Thompson, recently out of the Navy, asks Melcher for his help in gathering materials for his biography of Robert Frost, 1946-1949 (Box-folder 6:54)